# 甘肃·兰州
Lanzhou, Gansu.
# 啊 走过了
Oh, I missed it.
# 现在是晚上6点钟 我们将要去一个羊杂店
It is 6 P.M., and we are heading to a lamb offal restaurant.
# 在兰州 如果说早上是属于牛的
In Lanzhou, if the morning belongs to the beef,
# 那么晚上 一定是属于羊的
then the night definetely belongs to the lamb.
# 早上呢 不用多说 就是卖牛肉面的多一些
In the morning, basically, there are lots of places selling beef noodle soup.
# 就像我今天早上刚吃的这一种
Like the one I just had this morning.
# 随着这个时间逐渐到了中午 到了晚上
When it gets to the afternoon and evening,
# 卖牛肉的食品逐渐少了
there won't be that many beef products anymore.
# 但是卖羊杂 羊蹄 这样的有关羊的食物逐渐多了起来
However, by the time you will see more lamb products such as lamb offal and lamb trotters.
# 今天下午呢 我们将前往这个巷子的深处
This evening, we are heading into this alley.
# 品尝羊杂 特色的羊杂
To try some lamb offal.
# 现在已经开始排队了 我们也赶快过去吧
They have already lined up over there, let's go.
# 用滚烫烫30秒
We will cook this in boiling soup for about 30 seconds.
# 切好了羊杂以后
After we chopped up the lamb offal,
# 先撒椒盐
we will add some salt and pepper,
# 然后就是蒜泥
and minced garlic.
# 爱吃辣子就调一点辣子
If you want it to be spicy you can add some red chili oil.
# 这就比较圆满了
This is a good dish.
# 这是蒜苗
Sprinkle some garlic sprouts on top.
# 这是椒盐羊肝
This is salt & pepper lamb liver
# 这盘是纯羊头肉
This right here, is lamb head meat.
# 我看又有羊杂汤又有凉拌的？
I saw that you can have either lamb offal soup or salad?
# 是 有凉拌羊杂和羊杂汤2种
Yes, we have two different kinds.
# 干拌羊杂味道好一些
But offal salad tastes better,
# 我们的特色就是干拌羊杂
which is our special.
# 是我们兰州本地的特色
Our local special.
# 干拌的调料比较足一些 味道好
The salad seasoning makes it more flavorful.
# 这是羊舌头
This is lamb's tougue.
# 哦 还看不出来呢
Oh, I didn't even recognize.
# 这个是混着卖的呀
Do you sell a mixture of lamb offal?
# 是 都可以 随便
Yes.
# 单独点其中一种可以 混合的也可以
You can order a specific organ or a medley
# 那我要一个最普通的 混着的羊杂
Then I will have a mixed lamb offal
# 再给加一个饼
with a flatbread as well.
# 11号在这
No.11 is right here.
# 我们要的是35块钱的大份的
We bought the large size, which is 35 RMB.
# 配的是一个饼
I also ordered a flatbread
# 11号
No.11.
# 谢谢
Thank you.
# 好浓重的蒜汁和醋的味道
The scent of garlic and vinegar is quite strong.
# 放眼望去 就是满眼的蒜汁和辣子
If you look at this dish, it's just full of garlic and chili.
# 以前吃羊杂 都是喝羊杂汤
I've only had lamb offal in a soup.
# 他们这边是把羊杂凉拌出来
But here they took out the offal and turned it into a salad.
# 我本来以为这个羊杂碎是点一盘
At first, I thought this was a shareable dish
# 然后大家围着一起吃
And we will eat together from one plate.
# 实际上呢 是一人点一盘
Actually the portion size is for just one person
# 吃的时候呢 还会配一碗羊汤
accompanied with a bowl of lamb broth.
# 这个羊杂是怎么做的呢 它是半熟之后
How do they prepare the offal? It was typically par-cooked at first.
# 然后就是客人点了之后 再用沸汤过几下
When an order comes in, they cook it again in the boiling soup.
# 最后就是放上辣子 蒜汁这些 端到我们的面前
After adding garlic and chili oil, the dish is ready to serve.
# 是不是感觉配饼刚刚好
Perfect with this flatbread
# 嗯
Yea.
# 这么配饼吃 刚刚好
It's delicious with the flatbread
# 这个肝 确实嫩
This lamb liver is so tender.
# 喝口汤
With some broth.
# 配这个汤 也很好
This combination is also awesome.
# 在这边吃饭 调料味会重很多
Dishes here typically have very strong flavors.
# 如果说 肉不够 光蘸一蘸这个料 我都能把饼吃完
Even without the meat I can eat the whole flatbread with only the seasonings in the plate.
# 下午 我只是要了羊杂
I only had lamb offal in the afternoon.
# 其实这边还有一种食物是我没有尝试的
However, there is another type of food that I have yet to try.
# 就是羊头
The lamb head.
# 你看 咱们要的羊杂里面是有羊脸肉的
Our lamb offal has meat from lamb's face.
# 这个羊头除去了羊脸肉之外
However, after removing the meat from the face,
# 剩下的部分 还可以当做一道菜
they can use the rest of the lamb head to make a separate dish.
# 这就是一套 羊脸和羊干头
This a whole set of lamb face and head.
# 干头供不应求
So many people want to order the lamb head.
# 那吃羊头吃什么
What can you eat from the lamb head?
# 吃眼睛 吃上颌
Eyes, upper jaw, etc.
# 大叔 咱们在这边做多久了
Sir, how long have you been running this restaurant?
# 我们原来在市场 的时候我们干了十几年
We used to be in the market for over a decade.
# 13年
13 years.
# 在这边 我们又干了8年 就这个铺子
And we have been in this place for 8 years.
# 刚开始就跟老伴两个人
After first, it was only me and my wife.
# 后来儿子就参加
Then, my son joined.
# 因为这个工作比较繁琐
Because this job is quite tedious.
# 也不是一个人 两个人就能干了的事情
It is not something that can be easily done with one or two persons.
# 现在我们这儿5个人都忙不过来 还得再增加人手
Now, even with five persons, we still need more employees.
# 吃完了羊杂 我又来到了正宁路小吃街
After having the lamb offal, we are now at Zhengning Road's Snack Street.
# 这边有一种甜品叫做 牛奶鸡蛋醪糟
There is a type of dessert called: Laozao (sweet fermented rice) with milk and egg .
# 我想来试一下
I want to try it.
# 走了这么久 我倒是发现了很多家卖牛奶鸡蛋醪糟的
I think there are quite a lot of shops that make this dessert.
# 有个有意思的现象就是
What's interesting is that,
# 凡是卖牛奶鸡蛋醪糟的 都是一个姓马的白胡子老爷爷
every shop that makes this dissert has a grandpa whose lastname is Ma.
# 除了位置不同 我感觉不到有什么样的区别
Other than location, I don't really feel any difference between those shops.
# 最后呢 我找了一家看起来还不错的牛奶鸡蛋醪糟来排队
Eventually, I lined up at a store that looks quite decent.
# 加醪糟 牛奶 白糖
Laozao, milk, and sugar.
# 10元一杯
10 RMB per cup.
# 我们是排了一圈
Our line looks like a circle.
# 我后面的小哥说 排队就像贪吃蛇一样
The person behind me said, the line is like a snake.
# 它这个是稀的 不是稠的 上面就是漂着蛋花
It is actually quite watery, not thick at all. There are some egg flowers on top.
# 还有呢 就是放了花生 葡萄干 黑白芝麻
There are also peanuts, raisins, and sesame seeds on top.
# 味道很像这个 叫什么 叫什么来
It smells like, like,
# 它的味道很像核桃露的味道
walnut milk.
# 闻着米酒的味道还是很冲的 喝起来完全感知不到
The rice wine flavor doesn't taste as strong as it smells.
# 可能每一杯的味道都不太一样
Probably because every cup tastes a little differently.
# 因为我在那个地方观察它的牛奶 米酒的比例
I have noticed that, the ratio of milk and rice wine
# 我感觉有的时候 好像勺数是不一样的
is different sometimes.
# 有的时候就是米酒多放点
Sometimes they put more rice wine,
# 有的时候就是牛奶多放点
sometimes more milk.
# 我以为鸡蛋和成了蛋花 放在里面 应该是均匀的状态
I thought the egg flowers should be mixed evenly within this dissert.
# 没想到 它和热的米酒牛奶放在一起
It surprised me that, mixing with hot rice wine and milk,
# 还是成了大的蛋花
the egg turned into even larger egg flowers.